it's on your pants
contentment with basic requisites
there's something that most people would
like to have if they thought about it to
be satisfied with that which is
available readily available to you
actually good enough food good enough
clothing big enough shelter and enough
medicine that's even though we have
those things available there's no
content there is no contentment because
there is no because people are careless
in regard to their desires contentment
requires maintenance it requires you to
[Music]
to foresee things before they arise to
foresee a possibility for proliferation
before it arises so it's just though
obviously is everything else that you if
somebody's just starting it's gonna be
unpleasant because of the discomfort and
it's gonna it's gonna require some doing
and learning but once a person develop
that habit then yeah they they don't
need to be constantly obsessing over
simplicity and and keeping things simple
and requisites because they will become
the way they prefer to live but until
until they reach that point you do need
to keep yourself in check pretty much it
just ask yourself well hold on do I need
this much do I need this many so can i
is this efficient and most often the
answer is yes absolutely and the reason
why people always go for more is because
of the unquestioned attitude towards
avoiding discomfort people don't want
discomfort so do I need mattress of that
thickness well no really but you know if
I don't if I don't have it sufficiently
comfortable I won't sleep at night well
you might not sleep first night or
second night great third now you'll be
so tired you'll sleep on a concrete
block so you train yourself in that
regard obviously you don't have to you
don't have to do it sort of without that
purpose as in just just try to pronounce
everything in and then not eat sleep on
a stone I mean you know if that brings
the unwholesome states to decrease and
wholesome states to increase here by all
means but doing it in itself because
sometimes people can get intoxicated
with that sort of the Tunga
determination which is misguided like
you're just doing it out of some sort of
match up you think to prove like yeah
you know I don't lay down when I sleep
and so on why
what's the relationship between that and
unwholesome states decreasing and also
states increasing usually ends up
increasing the conceit and so on so you
always want to keep it practical that's
how you know you won't be able to kind
of wear off too far into into conceited
determination of I'm the best I'm the
toughest keep it practical I think that
I'm genuinely practical things that are
not necessary that can then support your
practice towards wakefulness and towards
diminishing of the unwholesome states so
yeah the little things you have to throw
everything away but you ask yourself is
my mattress too soft could I sleep on a
harder surface why would why would the
result be will be less sleep because you
wouldn't be able to overly enjoy it's
not comfortable which means okay so that
could bring the unwholesome states to
decrease in all some states to increase
means I won't be indulging in the sleep
so you remove your mattress and sleep on
a wooden board but if you're doing it
out of some sort of self advertisement
as well I mean it's you can still arrive
it can still be made wholesome
so in a way it still it's still okay but
it's important to distinguish it to
whether it's done out of just some sort
of inspiration on determination or if
it's done for the purpose of practically
supporting your practice becoming
stronger tougher you can take more than
and you'll be bored less because you can
take more you can take physical pain [Laughter]
[Laughter]
well yeah if you if your body is
dependent on certain amount of comfort
well you would struggle if you were to
leave the softness of your home your
environment your bedroom you would
struggle you know so ask yourself like
is my current situation really making me
tougher and able to do the elements as
the Buddha said that you should because
you know some of the tensor to be
abandoned by enduring so you can ask
yourself honestly then well would I be
abandoning any of those things if I
can't even give up my five inch mattress
yet you're supposed to be enduring cold
and heat mosquitoes and insects
discomfort evening meal is it necessary
we like will I die if I don't eat until
tomorrow well this hunger kill me am I genuinely
well this hunger kill me am I genuinely
like fainting and I don't know losing
losing my senses no no so it's just a
bit of discomfort it off in terms of
shelter trying to get your surrounding
Josh in terms of your shelter perfectly
spiritual way so that you can well no
that's that's what that's all loosening
that is I said that misguided
inspiration in determination it's just
it's more like it's more on a level of
people's identity and what they do and
what they're practicing it's not really
rooted properly on the level of actually
trying to uproot the identity belongings
appropriation sensor self life in
existence you know people have a little
shrine set up I mean again we have to
differentiate we're talking about it
like a casual layperson who is
practicing oh you're talking about
somebody who is really sort of going for
it
committed to it full-on if you're just
doing it pattern that's fine these
little reminders can be helpful because
well yeah you're not you're not giving
up the life but if you were actually a
monk or something like that then yeah
it's not really I mean a monk was
practicing toward ara and support or
towards understanding that I'm at least
Snickers shrines can be focuses your
intention really I mean again as I said
if you live a busy lady life and you
have no intention of leaving it then
yeah a little shrine can remind you of
certain values in the same sense the
Buddha said yeah like if you're not
doing anything else going visit the
place with the target that was born and
so on because he will make you think
about him as in think about the values
of enlightenment but having shrine of
worship a shrine for the sake of your
practice well it's just completely makes
no difference literally it's neither
contributing well it could be taking
away if you think that's what practice
is but I think most people one thing
that a bit of some sort of pleasing
identity shrine which is fine but if you
want to arrive at any any relevant
distinction that needs to be overcome in
terms of the benefits of community life
for a monk as opposed to living alone
do you think it's good for someone a
month to start off in a community or
just go straight into seclusion yeah
take on the suitors me the suitors well
it depends on the community and also
depends on the monk as in how much self
transparency has that person developed
beforehand they might be able to make it
because there's this dumb a part of
verse says I'm a sixty one if in your
course you don't meet your equal your
better then continue your course firmly
alone there's no fellowship with fools well I
there's no fellowship with fools well I
mean that that refers to somebody is not
chosen sotapanna because he already
knows what equal to sort but isn't
another person with the right view okay
then you will be living harmoniously
otherwise you're just pairing yourself
with fools unless they're there to learn
from you which is a different type of
relationship the person who is starting
cannot apply that verse because they
don't really know what the criteria is
for the review and for them equal or
better but that's why I mean if they're
self transparent as in they're really
looking internally those things that one
should be looking at then theoretically
yeah they could probably go straight
more secluded environment but highly
likely today because there are other
things that you can learn necessary
things interaction because of today the
Buddhism is is pretty much inseparable
from its respective tradition yeah
ideally Buddhism is not a tradition and
it didn't used to be but you can't
expect today to be just some pure pure
setup it's always gonna have some
traditional influence which means you
always need to know at least to a degree
how to relate to it as in learned
basically but that brings to the next
point of well it depends on the
community because some communities might
be a bit too obsessed about the random
tradition that has nothing to do with
the practice of Dhamma and it's all
about that or it's all about full-on
control telling people what to do and so
which you don't necessarily sign up for
but I think there are a person is clear
with internally by themselves with
themselves what they what they want and
then taking a step back as in donut over
act out of that inspiration and I'm sure
a person can find suitable enough place
where you could strike the balance
between well learning certain yeah
ultimately unnecessary things but
practically necessary things and having
having time to practice which is soft
correctly with the suitors and and
everything else
there's another pursuit our readouts and
Gujarat 8 verse 30
is that the dumbest one for is for one
who is reclusive not for one who is
entangled and thus was it said with
reference to what what it said there is
a case where a monk when living in
seclusion is visited by monks nuns
laymen labor and with his mind bent on
seclusion tending towards seclusion
inclined toward seclusion aiming at
seclusion enjoying renunciation he
converses with them only as much as is
necessary for them to take their leave
this Dhamma is one for one who is
reclusive not for one in entanglement
no that's that's the thing you have to
as I said you have to find that balance
or to find a place that has a balance
like there are monasteries in Thailand
for example where you'd mean in the
morning 4-pin depart and chores and the
rest of the day you're on your own you
could practice in seclusion but within
the community if something comes up
occasionally they would be getting
together to study 20 months whatever
beam is on and that's all fine but then
on the other hand you have those
monasteries were sort of have all these
goodies but then you constantly have to
be mingling with each other so despite
having the potential for that kind of
reclusive life and a minimum of coming
together and socializing you end up
spending most of their socializing Oh at
at 5 o'clock where puja at 6 o clock
within the blood-red o clock we have
chose the 10 o clock we have meal at 1
o'clock we'll clean up after the meal at
3 o clock we have I don't know dying
robe session it's 5 o'clock we have tea
and 6 o'clock we have puja at 9 o clock
you go to UT alone well that's not
Benton's included is constantly living
with a group and there is there is a
genuine factor of being physically
secluded like in comparison to a busy
lay light show a group of people in the
monastery are quieter and more secluded
but fundamentally from the point of view
of practicing the demo correctly
physical seclusion is necessary even if
you're not talking to each other sitting
next to each other throughout a day
meditating together well you're still
not physically secluded and to that
extent you're a loss so that's what I
mean to find that balance whereby there
will be some interaction certainly for
the first few nice IR years but but then
that doesn't mean like to subscribe to
80% of your day interaction it quickly
gets out of hand
because ultimately you're training to be
able to live entirely alone but the only
way to train that is to start being
alone bit by bit by bit but if you spend
your time just constantly being with
others well you're certainly not
training in solitude and that's why many
many people from the from the busy
communities would be quite well they
wouldn't be at ease if they were just
dropped in a random forest cookie on
their own it would take time to get used
to it if the gate is dead solid is what
some people genuinely scared the idea
what even going going into the
environment that nobody can speak
English for example but yeah you can't
expect to be able to do it overnight but
unless you're trying you're certainly
not gonna do it over hundreds of nights
you just want it won't happen overnight
no magically by itself so that that
needs to be your goal so if you
recognize the weakness in yourself that
you're afraid to be alone or or you
might not be able to handle it you have
to start training and exposing yourself
to it bit by bit by bit which means that
the monitoring has to at least support
it has the least allow possibility for
it
so what is the benefits other than
learning the rules well the benefit
could also be that the gradual exposure
to solitude but your aim is solitude
from the start and then gradually expose
yourself so when you reach a point where
yeah you can live alone now well if your
aim is to be more conducive to others in
the world where you go whatever there's
a human being you can be conducive okay
yeah so you should be aiming for
solitude because solitude is necessary
for our hardship and that's the ultimate
conduciveness for others freedom from
greed aversion delusion just community
life can challenge you another season
some mutiny Kyle 21 verse 10 an elder
monk who lives alone and the blessed one
says to him he's a truth elder that you
live alone and extol the virtues on
living alone it's yes Lord but how do
you live alone install the virtues of
living alone Lord alone I enter the
village for elms alone I returned alone
I sit with withdrawn and meditation
alone I do walking meditation that is
how I live alone and extol the virtues
when living alone so the Buddha says
there is that way of living alone I
don't say that there there isn't still
listen well to how you're living alone
is perfected in his details and play pay
close attention I will speak
so this one said and how is living alone
perfected in his details there is the
case where whatever is in his past is
abandoned whatever his future is relinquished and
whatever his future is relinquished and
any passion and desire with regard to
states of being being attained in the
present is well subdued that is how
living alone is perfected in its details
all conquering all knowing intelligent
with regard to all things
undead hearing all abandoning released
released in the ending of craving he
might call a man who lives alone whether
it was a battery like he's a film it how
many minutes 90 sir
okay so so saying that's that's how you
truly live the lines to abandon trade
yeah well that bring me to the to the
other point I should have mentioned
before is that sometimes people of monks
can use solitude as a form of avoiding
things as in you don't you could to you
lock yourself in and then just because
you don't want to deal with anything but
that Daddy that that includes do you
want to deal with with hardship
discomfort so that's that's also done
for wrong reasons
which means you need to be you need to
be making sure that your motivation to
the solitude is rooted toward practice
not so not towards avoiding not oh it's
just not being hassled by unpleasant
things so you just lock it or you don't leave
so you just lock it or you don't leave
at all and you can you can easily see
whether it's rooted in that just just
sometimes somebody will come to your
cookies and see if you were upset are
you upset that somebody's disturbing a
solitude if you are means you you're
holding on to it wrongly or if you're
overly joyed that somebody came to your
cookie be cool it means okay so you're
struggling with solitudes you're just
just looking for distraction but either
of those things or rather both of those
things can be overcome on the basis of
solitude not on the basis of socializing
that's like that that is soot I don't
know which one but I remember reading it
where the Buddha said even if a monk
goes and lives in the forest and he just
spends his time sleeping and being
sluggish and not practicing
well eventually his mind will will sort
of calm down and get established upon
that seclusion and then the wholesome
states will increase on the other hand
you have amongst hooting hoot monk who
live near the village and although he's
not sluggish and I'm mindful because he
lives near a village where people
frequenting and coming he will decline
there he won't raise so that's what I
mean the solid should needs to be their
basis but obviously it's not a goal in
itself and that's what the Buddha points
out in this suit it's good that you're
alone yeah that's for more solid
but now you want to take that solitude
to the point of understanding and
freeing yourself from the devil delusion
from desire which is how you're truly
alone
you know abandoned in the past yeah
exactly abandoning the past abandoned
like abandoning the abandoning the
emotional connection with the past when
people you know when that's why people
are afraid to be alone because the mind
starts thinking about things they were
done in the past could have been done or
shouldn't have been done and all that it
just becomes a serial can be a serious
issue or ends up thinking what I'm gonna
do tomorrow can't wait for tomorrow and
I'm gonna meet people and then do this
and then do that we're hoping for things
tomorrow to come up to be done so I
won't be in solitude because I find it
too hard so yeah he abandons that and
then he fully discerns much presently
there and that's how he's truly alone so
how to not procrastinate so
procrastinate you know put things off
like I said one suitor says I have to go
on a long journey tomorrow a bit a bit
of rest now so I can't have time to
practice but do you know things to do
tomorrow oh right
I just recovered from an illness sure
I've got it you know take it easy calm
practice I am you know and then it's the
opposite oh I am here I might not have
time well that's exactly how do not
procrastinate you have to say what to
think of the alternative as well well
wait a minute what's what's more
important to rest and go on a trip
tomorrow there might be unavoidable but
that's not the question the question is
which is more important the random trip
that happened to be unavoidable due to
circumstances or your practice of dumb
so you know the answer it's far more
important practice so then you make sure
that whenever you can practice you
practice it and you don't use other
things that are not equally important as
an excuse to not make gift or dumb again
it's it simplifies your life by having a
clear goal it does yeah exactly
nothing else sure yeah no that's that's
that's exactly what it contributes it's
not about the ropes shelter not about
plays yeah so why do that we come up
Yeti and they make sure you relate to
that answer why did I become a monk to
practice Dhamma oh so is there a
connection with a track Sudama as in am
i practicing Dhamma
or has it just been sort of pushed in
some sort of abstract background whereby
yes of course I'm here to practice
Dhamma but really practically your
choices and things you do have nothing
to do it breaks you develop it doesn't
mean you don't go and don't do anything
wrong things don't necessarily need to be a
things don't necessarily need to be a
distraction but you don't want to be
doing anything on account of doing the
dumb practice so if you can do other
thing within that price Sudama that's
fine but that's tempore debts the
criteria that's the that's the criteria
you use to judge the other types of
activity
and he does again comes down to what we
spoke before being practical as in doing
things have practical purpose
regression is just lazy you might have
those reason this place
well yeah laziness is a factor lack of
energy laziness sloth and Tocco but that's
laziness sloth and Tocco but that's
that's one of the entrances it needs to
be overcome because you're practicing
the Dharma correctly as in not
tolerating the unwholesome states in
your mind making effort to not engage
with them and making effort for the
wholesome states for mindfulness to be
established and so on it's it's
diligence it's a proper diligence start
doing the work when work is necessary
imagine a chore just presents itself and
you just have to go into it
you can't postpone it like living right
here when it starts to rain for example
and you roofer to suddenly new luckily
it wasn't there before you have to go
and fix it despite the discomfort of
heavy wind and rain you end up hanging
off the roof but you have to go and fix
it because otherwise well you're gonna
wait until tomorrow but you might not
stop the rain and then will you be
flooded inside so imagine how much more
important then is to have that kind of
attitude towards the unwholesome States
to abandon them into as wholesome States
to cultivate them so that's why it's
diligence it's not diligence because you
know you walk like a like a slow-motion
robot to preserve every moment the past
is you committed to the point of
neurosis no it's diligence because you
recognize the work and you always do it
you don't procrastinate
there is the unwholesome that's the
death suit over the Buddha was a fear
and dread said if I would be walking and
then some fear or unwholesome states
arose I wouldn't change the posture
until I dispel it first that was done
firstly because he did if he were to act
out of it sorry if he were to change his
posture account of that fear poor or
unwholesome states his action would have
been rooted in that unwholesome state so
he want to prevent that and also he
wanted to prevent postponing of dealing
with whatever says there isn't no I'll
move after I finish this he has a reason
that's the work for you yeah you didn't
ask for it
it doesn't mean you're not responsible
because that all it takes we done
wholesome states to ignore them and then
you'll be acting out of them Huijin
brings more unwholesome states which
then you can own that's that's why it's
so easy to be ignorant to give in to
lost and aversion that's why it's
natural with the grain so that's what
the diligent of practice is is earning
that not tolerating not welcoming you
know not denying it either it has a
reason that's fine but being able to
withstand it being able to allow it to
persist while it's changing sort of
while it's becoming different yet still
the same being able to do it it
basically that's what I'm saying
without acting out of it without
ignoring it without trying to distract
yourself from it
and that requires what actions yeah so
you're avoiding the responsibility even
if you´d is because of your past actions
it doesn't matter how the fear arose or
why what matters is that what you're
doing now in regard to it how do you are
you acting out of it by running away
from it you're trying to get rid of it
if yes that's your responsibility
there's a matter even if you did arise
because your past actions makes no
difference abandoning the past yeah that's how you
abandoning the past yeah that's how you
been in the past in that present
they often housing sites and we do
exactly you don't distract yourself from
it if it's unwholesome in terms of
sensuality but you don't indulge it you
don't welcome it you don't entertain it
you don't let it linger as in as in with
like allowing attitude and that's also
the cultivating of wholesome
automatically sure exactly it's not like
okay now I've dispelled unwholesome let
me find the wholesome to do no
dispelling unwholesome it's what
wholesome is hence automatically if
you're reducing unwholesome you're
automatically increasing the wholesome
if you're decreasing also you are
increasing on also to the same extent
they cannot coexist
which means you need to you need to have
solitude to be able to have clarity of
your thoughts because if you're
constantly distracted with communication
with others sounds of others you won't
you won't develop the same level of
discernment so if you do live in
solitude but then don't just do some
sort of things to distract you from
yourself and often people end up doing
meditation for that purpose or sit and
meditate because if they just sit and do
nothing it becomes a bit too much that's
the whole point that's what you're
training against you want to be able to
think properly without without being
overwhelmed by that fear of boredom or
anxiety in that solitude because how can
you discern presently arisen unwholesome
thought or wholesome thought if you
refusing to think if you're just trying
to shut the thinking out how can you
work exactly so you need to start
thinking and allowing those thoughts to
rise and then learning how not to act
and then learning how to remove the
attitude of welcoming the central
thoughts remove the attitude of trying
to get rid of the unpleasant thoughts
because the thoughts are on the problem
it's that attitude based on how you feel
in regard to them that's the problem but
if you're ignoring them trying to stop
thinking or whatever else
how can you see the problem and if you
don't see the problem hockey is all
about
even if you're not successful so we'd
agree at least you're doing that work
well exactly the success can come out of
the right type of work there's a
persistence yeah trial and error is the
right well that's why you don't get more
specific instruction in the suitors he's
diligent he rises energy he doesn't he
doesn't tolerate unwholesome he
cultivates wholesome yes that is the
closest you can get in terms of
instructing somebody their persistence
have I attained that which hasn't been
attained no excuse thankful for lacking
energy he doesn't use everything
everything then becomes aim for that
dead right purpose and if you pair that
with how we started this whole
discussion having a degree of discomfort
in your life yeah they will keep you
keep you well he will keep you mindful
of that basis because you might think on
I'm striving problem call to cultivating
while your whole life revolves around
comfort access to to to to to medicines
and robes and cushy bedrooms and so on
so you ask yourself well actually
is there a likelihood of this being an
impediment and more often than not the
answer is yes but if you have a degree
of discomfort you can't get too
complacent so then even on the days when
you really don't have much energy well
you won't be too complacent as in you
won't be too lazy cuz you can't because
you can't sleep too much on a hard
wooden plank it's too cold to just sort
of you know sit and do nothing
so you just keeps your mind sharp that's
why usually solitude and a degree of
discomfort made obviously for different
people various would would be would be
bringing the unwholesome states to
decrease and also states to increase
cuz you just kind of fought saturated you